[
  {
    "question": "ISRO has successfully maneuvered the Chaser and Target satellites to a 3-meter range under which programme, aimed at testing the indigenous Bharatiya Docking System?",
    "options": [
      "Gaganyaan",
      "SpaDex",
      "Chandrayaan 4",
      "Bhartiya Antriksh Station",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "SpaDex"
  },
  {
    "question": "When will the first Lokpal Day be celebrated?",
    "options": [
      "14th January 2025",
      "15th January 2025",
      "16th January 2025",
      "17th January 2025",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which automobile manufacturer launched the first locally produced iX1 Long Wheelbase electric SUV?",
    "options": [
      "Audi",
      "Mercedes-Benz",
      "Tata",
      "BMW",
      "Ford"
    ],
    "answer": "BMW"
  },
  {
    "question": "The RBI has constituted a committee for the Framework on Responsible and Ethical AI (FREE-AI) in the financial sector, chaired by ________, to ensure ethical adoption, governance, and risk management.",
    "options": [
      "Dr. Rajiv Kumar, NITI Aayog Vice Chairman",
      "Dr. C. Rangarajan, Former RBI Governor",
      "Dr. Raghuram Rajan, Economist and Former RBI Governor",
      "Dr. Pushpak Bhattacharyya, Professor, IIT Bombay",
      "Dr. Abhijit Banerjee, Nobel Laureate in Economics"
    ],
    "answer": "Dr. Pushpak Bhattacharyya, Professor, IIT Bombay"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Indian institution ranked 99th in computer science in THE World Rankings 2025, marking the first time an Indian institution has been in the global top 100 for this subject?",
    "options": [
      "IIT Bombay",
      "IIT Delhi",
      "IISc Bengaluru",
      "IIT Madras",
      "IIT Roorkee"
    ],
    "answer": "IISc Bengaluru"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has won Best Performance by a Male Actor in a Limited Series, Anthology Series, or a Motion Picture Made for Television at the Golden Globe Awards 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Adrian Brody",
      "Colin Farrell",
      "Tadanobu Asano",
      "Jeremy Allen White",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Cabinet approved setting up the 8th Pay Commission to revise the salaries of central government employees and pensioners. How many employees and pensioners will be affected by it?",
    "options": [
      "49 lakh employees and 65 lakh pensioners",
      "50 lakh employees and 71 lakh pensioners",
      "45 lakh employees and 60 lakh pensioners",
      "66 lakh employees and 55 lakh pensioners",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Indian Navy commissioned its latest multi-role stealth-guided missile frigate, INS Tushil. Which of the following statement/statements is/are correct?\n1 - Guided missile frigate INS Tushil (F 70) was commissioned into the Indian Navy at Kaliningrad, Russia, by Defence Minister Rajnath Singh.\n2 - The INS Tushil is an upgraded Krivak-III class frigate under Project 1135.6.\n3 - The INS Tushil joined the \"Sword Arm of the Indian Navy\", the Western Fleet, under the Western Naval Command.",
    "options": [
      "Only 1",
      "Only 2 and 3",
      "Only 1 and 3",
      "All of the above are correct.",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "All of the above are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which renowned botanist, known for translating Hortus Malabaricus into English and Malayalam, passed away at 86?",
    "options": [
      "K S Manilal",
      "Janaki Ammal",
      "Birbal Sahni",
      "Ashutosh Pawar",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "K S Manilal"
  },
  {
    "question": "With which organization did the Financial Intelligence Unit-India (FIU-IND) sign an MoU on January 6, 2025, to enhance cooperation in combating money laundering?",
    "options": [
      "Reserve Bank of India (RBI)",
      "Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI)",
      "Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDAI)",
      "Ministry of Finance",
      "National Financial Reporting Authority (NFRA)"
    ],
    "answer": "Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDAI)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country is hosting the 1st International Pashmina Festival to promote \"Chyangra Pashmina\"?",
    "options": [
      "India",
      "Bhutan",
      "Pakistan",
      "Nepal",
      "Afghanistan"
    ],
    "answer": "Nepal"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the joint venture announced by Trump for AI infrastructure development?",
    "options": [
      "AI Bridge",
      "Quantum Nexus",
      "FutureLink",
      "Stargate",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which state has topped the Fiscal Health Index (FHI) 2025 ranking launched by NITI Aayog?",
    "options": [
      "Chhattisgarh",
      "Odisha",
      "Goa",
      "Jharkhand",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the slogan for the UAE's 2025 \"Year of Community\" initiative announced by President Sheikh Mohamed bin Zayed Al Nahyan?",
    "options": [
      "Together We Can",
      "United We Stand",
      "Hand in Hand",
      "Building Bridges",
      "Lets Stand"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many Arjuna Awards for outstanding performance in Sports and Games were announced in 2024?",
    "options": [
      "20",
      "29",
      "32",
      "26",
      "35"
    ],
    "answer": "32"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) has approved the voluntary amalgamation of The National Co-operative Bank Ltd., Bangalore, with ________, effective from January 06, 2025.",
    "options": [
      "Saraswat Co-operative Bank Limited",
      "Punjab and Maharashtra Co-operative Bank",
      "Cosmos Co-operative Bank Limited",
      "Shamrao Vithal Co-operative Bank",
      "Bharat Co-operative Bank"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which veteran filmmaker will receive the Padmapani Lifetime Achievement Award at the Ajanta-Ellora International Film Festival 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Mira Nair",
      "Aparna Sen",
      "Sai Paranjpye",
      "Shyam Benegal",
      "Vivek Rathore"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which countries officially became full members of the Schengen Border-Free Zone on January 1, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Ukraine and Moldova",
      "Serbia and Montenegro",
      "Romania and Bulgaria",
      "Croatia and Slovenia",
      "Greece and Turkey"
    ],
    "answer": "Romania and Bulgaria"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the theme of the 15th edition of Asia's biggest aero show, Aero India 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Wings of Innovation",
      "The Sky's the Limit",
      "Advancing Atmanirbhar Aerospace for All",
      "The Runway to a Billion Opportunities",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "The Runway to a Billion Opportunities"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who won the men's and women's singles titles at the 2025 Australian Open?",
    "options": [
      "Novak Djokovic and Iga Swiatek",
      "Jannik Sinner and Madison Keys",
      "Carlos Alcaraz and Aryna Sabalenka",
      "Daniil Medvedev and Elena Rybakina",
      "Carlos Alcaraz and Elena Rybakina"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which project do INS Vaghsheer belong to?",
    "options": [
      "Project 75",
      "Project B",
      "Project 15B",
      "None of the above",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Project 75"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which satellite is ISRO set to launch to enable direct smartphone voice calls from space?",
    "options": [
      "Voyager Satellite",
      "Starlink Satellite",
      "Artemis Satellite",
      "Bluebird Satellite",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Bluebird Satellite"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the regulatory inclusion of NaBFID as an All-India Financial Institution (AIFI):\n1. NaBFID will be regulated by the Reserve Bank of India under Sections 45L and 45N of the RBI Act, 1934.\n2. It is permitted to participate in financial markets through activities like Credit Default Swaps (CDS) and Repo Transactions.\n3. NaBFID was established as India's sixth All-India Financial Institution (AIFI) to provide long-term infrastructure financing.\nWhich of the following options is correct?",
    "options": [
      "Only 1",
      "Only 1 and 2",
      "Only 2 and 3",
      "Only 1 and 3",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Department of Administrative Reforms and Public Grievances has released the scheme guidelines for the National e-Governance Awards 2025. The Awards will consist of a Trophy, Certificate, and an incentive of Rs. ______ for Gold Awardees and Rs. ______ for Silver Awardees.",
    "options": [
      "5 lakhs, 3 lakhs",
      "10 lakhs, 7 lakhs",
      "15 lakhs, 10 lakhs",
      "10 lakhs, 5 lakhs",
      "7 lakhs, 3 lakhs"
    ],
    "answer": "10 lakhs, 5 lakhs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the initiative launched to empower elected women representatives from Panchayati Raj institutions:",
    "options": [
      "Training Women Leaders Program",
      "Empowering Women in Governance",
      "Women Empowerment in Panchayats",
      "Panchayat Se Parliament",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Panchayat Se Parliament"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was sworn in as a Supreme Court judge on January 16, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Justice R. Banumathi",
      "Justice S. Ravindra Bhat",
      "Justice K Vinod Chandran",
      "Justice Siddappa Sunil Dutt Yadav",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Justice K Vinod Chandran"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following has been elected as a board member of the Marylebone Cricket Club (MCC) Advisory Board in January 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Kumar Sangakkara",
      "Jay Shah",
      "Sourav Ganguly",
      "Rahul Dravid",
      "Sanjay Bangar"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed as the Chairman and Managing Director (CMD) of the Food Corporation of India (FCI)? (January 2025)",
    "options": [
      "Rajiv Bansal",
      "Anil Kumar Jain",
      "Ashutosh Agnihotri",
      "Ajay Bhushan Pandey",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Ashutosh Agnihotri"
  },
  {
    "question": "India became an observer state in which international programme focused on intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance?",
    "options": [
      "Eurodrone",
      "Global Hawk",
      "Skyshield",
      "NATO Surveillance Programme",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Eurodrone"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Faral Sakhi Initiative, launched by the Mira Bhayandar Municipal Corporation in collaboration with the Women Entrepreneurship Platform (WEP) of NITI Aayog, aims to empower women entrepreneurs by providing training and support for which of the following activities?",
    "options": [
      "Tailoring and garment manufacturing",
      "Production and sale of traditional festive snacks",
      "Handicrafts and artisanal products",
      "Organic farming and agriculture",
      "Beauty and wellness services"
    ],
    "answer": "Production and sale of traditional festive snacks"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organization has given preliminary consent to sponsor the 38th National Games being hosted by Uttarakhand?",
    "options": [
      "Oil and Natural Gas Corporation (ONGC)",
      "Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Limited (HPCL)",
      "Bharat Petroleum Corporation Limited (BPCL)",
      "Indian Oil Corporation (IOC)",
      "BHEL"
    ],
    "answer": "Indian Oil Corporation (IOC)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sector in India was the most affected by cyberattacks in 2024, according to CloudSEK's Threat Landscape Report?",
    "options": [
      "Healthcare and pharma",
      "Financial and banking",
      "Telecommunications",
      "Education",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Financial and banking"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the India's OTT aggregator with which has BSNL partnered and launched IFTV Pilot in order to bolster inclusive digital connectivity and entertainment for every Indian in UP East?",
    "options": [
      "Zee5",
      "SonyLIV",
      "Hotstar",
      "OTTplay",
      "JioCinema"
    ],
    "answer": "OTTplay"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the RBI's circular on resetting floating interest rates for EMI-based personal loans:\n1. Interest rates must be reset at least once every three months for applicable loans.\n2. Borrowers must be informed about changes in EMI/tenor due to interest rate resets during the loan tenure.\n3. Urban Cooperative Banks (UCBs) are allowed a maximum 25-year loan tenor for housing loans under the new guidelines.\nWhich of the following options is correct?",
    "options": [
      "Only 1",
      "Only 1 and 2",
      "Only 1 and 3",
      "Only 2 and 3",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Only 1 and 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has been appointed as the Chief Executive Officer (CEO) of NASSCOM Foundation with immediate effect from January 2, 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Nidhi Bhasin",
      "Jyoti Sharma",
      "Debjani Ghosh",
      "Aruna Sundararajan",
      "Ritu Anand"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which space agency successfully germinated black-eyed pea seeds in space under the CROPS-1 mission?",
    "options": [
      "NASA",
      "ESA",
      "Roscosmos",
      "ISRO",
      "JAXA"
    ],
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which renowned Sanskrit scholar, honored with Padma Shri and Knight of the Legion of Honour, passed away in December 2024?",
    "options": [
      "Sheldon Pollock",
      "Pierre-Sylvain Filliozat",
      "Frits Staal",
      "Vasundhara Kavali Narorji",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Pierre-Sylvain Filliozat"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary goal of the Indian Sustainable Natural Rubber (iSNR) initiative?",
    "options": [
      "To prevent deforestation and support sustainable rubber production",
      "To increase the yield of rubber trees",
      "To focus on enhancing rubber product exports",
      "To reduce the cost of rubber production via supply-chain management",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "To prevent deforestation and support sustainable rubber production"
  },
  {
    "question": "Nepal launched the 'Child Marriage Free Nepal' campaign with support from Indian and Nepalese organizations. Who led the 'Child Marriage Free Nepal' campaign along with child rights activists?",
    "options": [
      "K P Sharma Oli",
      "Kishor Sah Sudi",
      "Just Right for Children",
      "BASE Nepal",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Kishor Sah Sudi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country became the 10th full member of BRICS in January 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Indonesia",
      "Myanmar",
      "China",
      "Finland",
      "Both 1 and 2"
    ],
    "answer": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which initiative was launched by Shri Jayant Chaudhary to empower underserved communities through skill development?",
    "options": [
      "Vocational Training Workshops",
      "Solar-Powered Skill Vans",
      "Digital Education Hubs",
      "Green Energy Skill Program",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Solar-Powered Skill Vans"
  },
  {
    "question": "From which age bracket did the NFHS 4 data reveal about 5% of women undergoing hysterectomy?",
    "options": [
      "15-24 years",
      "25-49 years",
      "50-60 years",
      "Above 60 years",
      "75-90 years"
    ],
    "answer": "25-49 years"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Lake Turkana\" is the largest desert lake in the world, it is situated in which of the following countries of the world?",
    "options": [
      "United Arab Emirates",
      "Turkey",
      "Kenya",
      "Oman",
      "Nigeria"
    ],
    "answer": "Kenya"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is India's total export value during April-December 2024, and what is the percentage growth compared to the previous period?",
    "options": [
      "USD 550.12 Billion, 5.02%",
      "USD 602.64 Billion, 6.03%",
      "USD 600.00 Billion, 5.50%",
      "USD 650.45 Billion, 7.00%",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which actor has been appointed as the first Brand Ambassador for FICCI Frames?",
    "options": [
      "Kartik Aaryan",
      "Ayushman Khurana",
      "Vicky Kaushal",
      "Ranveer Singh",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Ayushman Khurana"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the theme of the Grameen Bharat Mahotsav 2025?",
    "options": [
      "Empowering Villages through Technology",
      "Building a Resilient Rural India for a Viksit Bharat 2047",
      "Economic Transformation through Cooperatives",
      "Sustainable Agriculture for Rural Development",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Building a Resilient Rural India for a Viksit Bharat 2047"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organization received Foreign Contribution Regulation Act (FCRA) approval from the Union Ministry of Home Affairs for receiving foreign funds?",
    "options": [
      "Central Tibetan Administration",
      "Tibetan Youth Congress",
      "Tibetan Government-in-Exile",
      "His Holiness the Dalai Lama Charitable Trust",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "His Holiness the Dalai Lama Charitable Trust"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country unveiled its first national autism strategy with AU$42.3 million in funding, aiming to improve inclusion and support for autistic individuals, focusing on education, employment, and diagnostic reforms?",
    "options": [
      "United Kingdom",
      "Australia",
      "Canada",
      "New Zealand",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Australia"
  },
  {
    "question": "By which year does India aim to achieve 500 gigawatts of non-fossil fuel-based energy capacity?",
    "options": [
      "2025",
      "2030",
      "2026",
      "2028",
      "2035"
    ],
    "answer": "2030"
  },
  {
    "question": "Renowned filmmaker Arun Roy, best known for his critically acclaimed films Bagha Jatin (2023) and Hiralal (2021), passed away at the age of 56. In which language did director Arun Roy primarily make his films?",
    "options": [
      "Bengali",
      "Hindi",
      "Tamil",
      "Marathi",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Bengali"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary objective of the recently launched 'PLI Scheme 1.1' for the steel industry?",
    "options": [
      "Promoting export-oriented steel production",
      "Boosting small-scale steel industries in rural areas",
      "Establishing new research centers for advanced metallurgy",
      "Enhancing steel production through Production Linked Incentives",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "Enhancing steel production through Production Linked Incentives"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the total expenditure approved by the Union Cabinet for the establishment of the Third Launch Pad (TLP) at ISRO's Satish Dhawan Space Centre, and within how many months is the project expected to be completed?",
    "options": [
      "₹3984 crore; 36 months",
      "₹3984 crore; 48 months",
      "₹4450 crore; 48 months",
      "₹3984 crore; 60 months",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under the National Health Mission (NHM) from 2021 to 2024, how many additional healthcare workers were employed?",
    "options": [
      "8 lakh",
      "10 lakh",
      "12 lakh",
      "15 lakh",
      "None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "3"
  }
]